<!DOCTYPE article [
  <!ENTITY R "<ulink url='http://www.r-project.org'>R</ulink>">
  <!ENTITY Cxx "<ulink url='http://www.Cplusplus.org'>C++</ulink>">
]>
<article xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org">
<para>
 XML is very convenient for a variety of different applications. It
is language neutral and provides a form of persistence.  It can
contain directives (<emphasis>processing instructions</emphasis>) for different
systems to aid interpretation of a document. It is a convenient form
for specifying and storing configuration files.  This is because it
provides a richer form than simple ASCII file, havin significant
semantic information, but simpler than most languages.
</para>
<para>
We need the facilities for reading XML in both R and S.
Ideally they should be similar. There are a myriad of 
good XML parsers written in C, &Cxx;, Java, etc.
We can use these to provide R-level user programming
API for reading XML.
</para>

<para>
The reason for wanting user-level programming capabilities are
reasonably obvious. Firstly, the focus of these languages is
high-level operations and for this reason they are usually easier to
use.  Secondly, the mechanics of parsing and reading an XML document
are reasonably unimportant. What is more complex is the conversion
from the XML form to a user-level datastructure.  While XML documentss
contain more information than simple ASCII files, they do not
necessarily contain information about what type to map them to in each
target system and how to do so. The example below of a job has no
counterpart in R and so the user must decide how to arrange the
resulting data read from the XML file.
</para>

<para>
As a first start, we use the <ulink url="http://www.jclark.com/xml">expat</ulink>
parser.  The <ulink url="http://rpmfind.net/veillard/XML/">Gnome-related
parser</ulink> didn't compile for me and that makes me
hesitant. Additionally, it is heavily DOM oriented which requires the
entire tree to be in memory. We may have more constraints for large
datasets, etc.. It is a validating parser however.
</para>

<para>
The basic approach is reasonable simple.  As elements/nodes in the
document are located, the parser notifies our routines. These in turn
call &R; functions associated with that node type (e.g element,
character data, entity, etc.)  and potentially even the element name
(e.g. body, h1, h2, etc.).  The user initiates the parsing by
specifying the name of the ``file'' or stream and a collection of
functions which are used for the different ``events''.  The collection
of functions can also refer to local data by using a closure.
</para>

<para>
The following is a simple example of an XML document
taken from the GNOME xml distribution.
We use it to illustrate how we might generate
an &R; structure from it.
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<job.xml>=
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<gjob:Helping xmlns:gjob="http://www.gnome.org/some-location">
  <gjob:Jobs>

    <gjob:Job>
      <gjob:Project ID="3"/>
      <gjob:Application>GBackup</gjob:Application>
      <gjob:Category>Development</gjob:Category>

      <gjob:Update>
        <gjob:Status>Open</gjob:Status>
        <gjob:Modified>Mon, 07 Jun 1999 20:27:45 -0400 MET DST</gjob:Modified>
        <gjob:Salary>USD 0.00</gjob:Salary>
      </gjob:Update>

      <gjob:Developers>
        <gjob:Developer>
        </gjob:Developer>
      </gjob:Developers>

      <gjob:Contact>
        <gjob:Person>Nathan Clemons</gjob:Person>
        <gjob:Email>nathan@windsofstorm.net</gjob:Email>
        <gjob:Company>
        </gjob:Company>
        <gjob:Organisation>
        </gjob:Organisation>
        <gjob:Webpage>
        </gjob:Webpage>
        <gjob:Snailmail>
        </gjob:Snailmail>
        <gjob:Phone>
        </gjob:Phone>
      </gjob:Contact>

      <gjob:Requirements>
      The program should be released as free software, under the GPL.
      </gjob:Requirements>

    </gjob:Job>

  </gjob:Jobs>
</gjob:Helping>
]]></programlisting>
Basically, as we start each tag, we call the appropriate function
and give it a string name and a named list of XML attributes.
</para>
<para>
The parse function looks something like the following.  The
\SArg{handlers} object is assumed to be a closure.  Its functions
modify its own data internally and then we return it so that one can
access the new data contents.
</para>
<para>
The addContext argument instructs the internal \C{} code whether to
build the index path of the position in the XML tree for this node.
In the absence of references, it can be used to identify sub elements
of a tree.

</para>
<para>
The useTagName argument allows the caller to specify whether there are
functions per element name or to use the standard event driven
interface which is startElement, endElement, externalEntity,
etc.
</para>
<para>
<table>
<title>Standard Event Handlers</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
<row><entry>startElement</entry></row>
<row><entry>endElement</entry></row>
<row><entry>text</entry></row>
<row><entry>externalEntity</entry></row>
<row><entry>startCdata</entry></row>
<row><entry>endCdata</entry></row>
<row><entry>comment</entry></row>
<row><entry>default</entry></row>
<row><entry>startNameSpace</entry></row>
<row><entry>endNameSpace</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<r:code><![CDATA[
xmlEventParse <- function(file, handlers=xmlHandler(), addContext = T, useTagName = F) {
 handlers <- .Call("R_XMLParse", file, handlers)
 return(handlers)
}
]]></r:code>
</para>

<para>
In our simple setup, we will provide a single handler for the start
of a new element.
<r:code><![CDATA[
xmlHandler <- function() {
  data <- list()
  startElement <- function(name, atts,...) {
    if(is.null(atts))
      atts <- list()
    data[[name]] <<- atts
  }
  text <- function(x,...) {
    cat("MyText:",x,"\n")   
  }
  comment <- function(x,...) {
    cat("comment", x,"\n")
  }
  externalEntity <- function(ctxt, baseURI, sysId, publicId,...) {
    cat("externalEntity", ctxt, baseURI, sysId, publicId,"\n")
  }
  entityDeclaration <- function(name, baseURI, sysId, publicId,notation,...) {
    cat("externalEntity", name, baseURI, sysId, publicId, notation,"\n")
  }

  foo <- function(x,attrs,...) { cat("In foo\n")}
  return(list(startElement=startElement, getData=function() {data},
               comment=comment, externalEntity=externalEntity,
                entityDeclaration=entityDeclaration,
                text=text, foo=foo))
}
</r:code>

<r:code>
h = xmlParse("Docs/test.xml")
</r:code>

An entirely different approach
involves reading the entire document into memory
and then 


<r:code><![CDATA[
characterOnlyHandler <- function() {
  txt <- NULL
  text <- function(val,...) {
   i
    txt <<- c(txt, val)
  }

  getText <- function() { txt }

  return(list(text=text, getText=getText))
}
]]></r:code>
</para>
</article>